<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A shock of corn coming in in its season. A sermon preached at the funeral of that ancient and eminent servant of Christ VVilliam Gouge, Doctor of Divinity, and late pastor of Black-Fryars, London, December the 16th, 1653. With the ample and deserved testimony that then was given of his life, by William Jenkyn (now) pastor of Black-Fryars, London.</title>
            <author>Jenkyn, William, 1613-1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87565</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J653</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E735_22</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202634</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862855</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862855</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115033</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87565)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115033)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 113:E735[22])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A shock of corn coming in in its season. A sermon preached at the funeral of that ancient and eminent servant of Christ VVilliam Gouge, Doctor of Divinity, and late pastor of Black-Fryars, London, December the 16th, 1653. With the ample and deserved testimony that then was given of his life, by William Jenkyn (now) pastor of Black-Fryars, London.</title>
                  <author>Jenkyn, William, 1613-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Gellibrand, at the Ball in Pauls-Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gouge, William, 1578-1653.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Job V, 26 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115033:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Shock of Corn Coming in In its Seaſon.</p>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at the Funeral of that Ancient and Eminent Servant of CHRIST WILLIAM GOUGE, Doctor of Divinity, and late Paſtor of <hi>BLACK-FRYARS, London,</hi> December the 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, 1653.</p>
            <p>With the ample and deſerved Teſtimony that then was given of his Life,</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM JENKYN (now) Paſtor of <hi>BLACK-FRYARS, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Gellibrand,</hi> at the <hi>Ball</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:115033:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of William Gouge, Professor of Theology</figDesc>
                  <head>EFFIGIES GUIL:GOUGE S.S. THEOLOGIAE PROFESS: QUI OBIIT AN<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 46. Dui 1653. AEtatis 79. Ministery in Black fr: Lon: </head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The <hi>Simile</hi> vs'd by the <hi>Temanite</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Of a <hi>ripe ſhock</hi> of <hi>Corne</hi> exprest him right.</l>
                     <l>How weighty were his eares with <hi>worth?</hi> and he</l>
                     <l>Who bent with <hi>Age,</hi> bowd with <hi>Humility.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>He <hi>(ripe)</hi> is <hi>reapt</hi> this harvest time we mourn,</l>
                     <l>Heere <hi>harvest-joy,</hi> onely befell the <hi>Corne.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>From th' <hi>World</hi> (the <hi>feild</hi>) to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                        <hi>grave</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                        <hi>barne</hi> hees gon</l>
                     <l>Yet tho he lost the <hi>feild,</hi> he th' <hi>Victory</hi> won.</l>
                     <l>Our Corns <hi>now</hi> bread. for men those workes of his</l>
                     <l>Are bread for God, <hi>himſelf</hi> now ſhewbread is.</l>
                  </lg>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115033:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Shock of Corn Coming in In its Seaſon.</p>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at the Funeral of that Ancient and Eminent Servant of CHRIST WILLIAM GOUGE, Doctor of Divinity, and late Paſtor of <hi>BLACK-FRYARS, London,</hi> December the 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, 1653.</p>
            <p>With the ample and deſerved Teſtimony that then was given of his Life,</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM JENKYN (now) Paſtor of <hi>BLACK-FRYARS, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Gellibrand,</hi> at the <hi>Ball</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:115033:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115033:3"/>
            <head>To my much eſteemed and beloved Friends, the Church of God in the Precinct of BLACK-FRYARS, <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou have (already) a <hi>double</hi> right to this Dedication; it is yours firſt as this enſuing Sermon was <hi>preacht,</hi> next as it is <hi>publiſht.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> This Sermon was preacht, as <hi>among</hi> you and <hi>to</hi> you, ſo <hi>concerning</hi> him who of late was your worthy Paſtor, and <hi>by</hi> him who is (though unworthy, yet,) your Pastor.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> This Sermon is <hi>publiſht,</hi> though a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my own <hi>inclination</hi> (for I know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by any my ſervices, but what more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves my bluſhing for their weakneſſe, then publication for their worth) yet at the earneſt entreaty, as of many <hi>others,</hi> ſo of ſundry of <hi>your ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:115033:4"/>
            <p>But there is a <hi>third</hi> and (that) a <hi>better</hi> right which I deſire you may have to this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Diſcourſe, and that is a right to it by <hi>practiſing</hi> of the truths contained in the <hi>Sermon,</hi> and by imbracing the Doctrines, and imitating the graces of your late emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Paſtor commended in the following <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Sermon ſlights not your <hi>patronage,</hi> but it earneſtly <hi>ſues</hi> to you for your <hi>practiſe.</hi> And tis my deſire, that the unreformed who ſhall reade the Relation of Doctor <hi>Gouge's</hi> faithful pains among them, may with <hi>god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſorrow</hi> for their unprofitableneſſe under his miniſtry, ſay what <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Butler did in the apprehenſion of his ingratitude to <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 41.9.</note> 
               <hi>I do remember my faults this day.</hi> If the duſt of a living Miniſters <hi>feet,</hi> and the ſweat of his <hi>brows,</hi> ſhall be a <hi>teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny againſt a gain-ſaying people,</hi> how loudly will the duſt of a dead Miniſters
<pb facs="tcp:115033:4"/>
               <hi>grave</hi> cry againſt them! Tis but a ſorry piece of devotion, with the Jews to <hi>paint the Sepulchres of the Prophets,</hi> and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend them when dead, with our lips, whom living, we diſcommended by our practiſe; and yet as <hi>Sampſon</hi> could take honey out of that dead Lion, with which he fought, and which he ſlew, when alive, it roar'd upon him, ſo nothing is more ordinary then for the wicked to voice up dead Miniſters for ſweet and bleſſed men, whom in their life-time for <hi>lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up their voice</hi> againſt their ſinnes, and labouring to rend them and their luſts aſunder, they bitterly oppoſed. Though when <hi>Moſes</hi> was dead, the people would have worſhipt him as a God (and this the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil knew and lik't when he contended to have had his Sepulchre made known) yet when he was living, they would have deſtroyed him,<note place="margin">Jude 9</note> &amp; <hi>he fear'd ſtoning by them.</hi> Even wicked <hi>Joram</hi> calls <hi>dying Eliſha,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 1</note> the <hi>Chariots of
<pb facs="tcp:115033:5"/>Iſrael and the horſmen thereof. 2</hi> Kin. <hi>13.14.</hi> The Papiſts, and common Proteſtants, who now ſpeak highly of Chriſt and call him their <hi>ſweet Saviour,</hi> had they lived in his dayes, and heard him Preach againſt their ſins, would have hated him more then now they hate the godly, for having but a drop of his Fountain, and but a faint reflection of that holineſs which much more gloriouſly ſhin'd forth in him. As it may be a work of <hi>much credit,</hi> ſo it <hi>is</hi> a work of <hi>little coſt</hi> to extoll the deceaſed ſervants of Chriſt. By their voices, ſinners are not moleſted in the proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their luſts, nor urged to any unpleaſing duties. It is not then the crying up of depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Saints and Ministers with our <hi>words,</hi> but imitating of them with our works and the praiſing them with the Language of the <hi>converſation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Horo andi propt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em, non ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an-di proper religionem. Aug de ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r l. c. <hi>55.</hi>
               </note> which ſhews the ſincerity of our love either to God or them; The <hi>bark</hi> of a tree may be carried away, upon a mans ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:115033:5"/>without any pains or difficulty; but it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires strength and labour to carry away the <hi>body</hi> of the tree; men may eaſily run away with the outward ſhell of good words and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsions, but the <hi>heart</hi> and <hi>life</hi> of Religion, which is that of the <hi>heart</hi> and <hi>life,</hi> men can hardly away with. The dint of this <hi>dilem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> will not be ſhunned. If the Ministers doctrine and life were <hi>bad,</hi> why are they ſo <hi>much</hi> as commended; if good, why not <hi>more</hi> then commended, why not <hi>practiſed</hi> and <hi>imitated</hi> alſo? If Chriſt were <hi>not a good maſter,</hi> why did the young man call him ſo? if he <hi>were a good maſter</hi> why did he not <hi>follow</hi> him alſo?</p>
            <p>You will not be offended with me for my plain dealing; If I be <hi>Jealous</hi> leſt this holy man hath bestowed his labour in vain upon many ſurvivors; they will (I truſt) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member whoſe jealouſie it imitates, <hi>Pauls;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and of what <hi>nature,</hi> he ſaith, his was, <hi>a godly
<pb facs="tcp:115033:6"/>jealouſie.</hi> If I fear the flattering of ſome more then of others, it is of thoſe whom I love moſt: you have by calling me to be your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, laid a ſtrong engagement upon me, to beware of ſoothing you into deſtruction, and to put you in remembrance of promoting more vigorouſly the power of godlineſſe, and of ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up Chriſt more throughly in your hearts, houſes, and congregation, in the <hi>expectation</hi> of, and <hi>ſupplication for</hi> which, I reſt, dear and much eſteemed Friends,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Black Fryars,</hi> 
                  <date>May the <hi>8<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 1654.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your faithfull and affectionate ſervant for the good of your ſouls. <hi>William Jenkyn.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115033:6"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Men, Brethren, and Fathers,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ere Prefaeces and Apologies ſutable either to the ſervice of the <hi>Day,</hi> or the diſpoſition of the <hi>Speaker,</hi> I might prefix a large Apologie to my enſuing Diſcourſe. Should I preface my own unworthineſſe to <hi>undertake,</hi> or inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency to <hi>go through</hi> the following employment, I might poſſibly by ſome be more ſuſpected of <hi>pride,</hi> than commended for <hi>modeſty.</hi> I am not ignorant that a proud heart, may oft lye under a ſelf-deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing tongue. And I have heard of ſome who put their prayſes to <hi>uſury,</hi> they diſpraiſing themſelves for <hi>a while,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Robinſons <hi>Obſervations.</hi>
               </note> that ſo they may receive their praiſe again with advantage. Touching my ſelf there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I ſhall onely ſay, that the dear reſpect which I owe and bear to the memory of this excellent man, Saint, Miniſter, Doctor <hi>William Gouge,</hi> hath made me break through the deep reſentment of my own inſufficiency to go through this work; and yet withal, that againſt this inability of mine, I have theſe <hi>three things</hi> which relieve me (and theſe I ſhould not mention to the inlarging of a Preface, which is beſt when leaſt, did they not tend to the honouring of this ſervant of Chriſt, which is one end of our meeting this day.)</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> Firſt, I look upon that as my (and not my leaſt) encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to this ſervice, which moſt may think my greateſt diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from undertaking it, and that is the <hi>eminent worth</hi> of this Excellent Man, whoſe Funeral this day, we celebrate; were I ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to commend ſome prophane perſon, or ſome profeſſor whoſe worth and unworthineſſe did hang in <hi>aequilibrio,</hi> and appear ſo even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ballanc'd, that none could tell which of them outweigh'd the other, I might wound my conſcience, blaſt my reputation, or (at leaſt) tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture my invention, either to finde out <hi>matter</hi> of commendation, or a fit <hi>manner</hi> of expreſſing thereof. But (Brethren) I think, I have as little cauſe, as ever had any who preached in this place, upon the like occaſion, either to fear reproofs from my own heart, or my many hearers, for giving a large teſtimony to the worth of this Excellent
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115033:7"/>Man, or to ſtudy ſolicitouſly for matter of praiſe, which is (as it were) <hi>Myrrha Libera,</hi> Myrrhe which drops freely of its own accord with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſqueezing or conſtraint.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lachrymae au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditorum laudes miniſtrorum.</note> It is likewiſe my encouragement, that you (my Auditors) bear <hi>a ſhare</hi> with me in this Funeral and following commendation. As the tears of a people are a Miniſters praiſe, when he himſelf preacheth in his life-time, ſo is their ſorrow for him no ſmall commendation to him when another is preaching of him after his death. I doubt not but very many in this great Aſſembly come hither, not to gaze, to ſee and be ſeen, but to mourn for the death of this eminent ſervant of Chriſt, and to ſprinkle ſome tears upon his Funeral Herſe. Confident I am, that could you turn your ſorrowful inſides, outward, (like that people who were wont to ſhew their funeral mourning onely by turning the inſide of their apparel outward) that mournfulleſt expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions would be as common among you, as true mourning is ſuitable to you, and that Sable would as well cover the People as it doth the Pulpit. If the Angels were ſo forward to attend upon a <hi>Lazarus</hi> when he dyed, as to carry him to his place of reſt, what readineſſe ſhould there be among <hi>Lazaruſſes,</hi> full of the ſores of ſin and miſery, to reſpect the Funeral of this <hi>dead Angel?</hi> I call him <hi>Angel,</hi> for ſo he was in his life time in regard of his <hi>Office,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and <hi>as an Angel</hi> now after his death, I doubt not but he is in Heaven.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> My third encouragement is this: I am call'd this day to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form a <hi>greater Work</hi> then to praiſe him, I am to preach the Word to you. God who hath called me unto the greater, to ſpeak from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to you, I truſt will enable me to perform the leſſer, I mean, the ſpeaking concerning this Reverend Man to you. I know, you long to hear what I ſhall ſay of him, and haply ſome do ſo, becauſe they would give vent to their ſorrows, though by their Eyes. I ſhall gratifie your deſire when I have firſt delivered my Errand from God to you, the ſum whereof you ſhall finde written, in</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:115033:7"/>
            <head>The 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Chapter of <hi>Job,</hi> Verſ 26. In theſe words.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Thou ſhalt come to thy grave in a full age, like as a ſhock of Corn cometh in, in his ſeaſon.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He words were ſpoken by <hi>Eliphaz</hi> to inforce that dehortation given to <hi>Job,</hi> Verſ 17. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe not thou the chaſtening of the Almighty:</hi> that is, Caſt it not off with a weariſome averſneſs, and loathing, nor reject it either as unprofitable and unuſeful, or as diſgraceful and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honourable to thee, nor ſlight it as a thing of which no notice is taken, &amp;c. This counſel he backs with an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument drawn from the <hi>benefit</hi> that ſhould accrue unto him, by a ſubmiſſiveneſſe under the afflicting hand of God. <hi>Eliphaz</hi> ſhews, that at length, the mercy of God, ſhall appear for his good; and that both, Firſt, by <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation</hi> from evils (Verſ 19. <hi>He ſhall deliver thee from ſix troubles, yea in ſeven, there ſhall no evil touch thee</hi>) and alſo, Secondly, by the <hi>beſtowing</hi> of bleſſings, Verſ 23, 24; 25. <hi>Thou ſhalt know that thy tabernacle ſhall be in peace, &amp;c.</hi> Yea he declares that <hi>Job</hi> ſhall not onely be happy in <hi>his life-time,</hi> but alſo even at and after <hi>his death,</hi> in the words of my Text, <hi>Thou ſhalt come to thy grave in a full age, like as a ſhock of corn cometh in, in his ſeaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:115033:8"/>
            <p>In which words, you have this two parts conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A godly mans <hi>arival at his</hi> Port, or terme, <hi>Thou ſhalt come to thy grave.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>ſeaſonableneſſe</hi> of this arival, <hi>in a full age, like as,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In the former, I take notice of <hi>two</hi> particulars,
<list>
                  <item>1. What that <hi>place</hi> or Port is, <hi>the grave.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. What that kind of <hi>paſſage</hi> to it is, which here is promiſed. <hi>Thou ſhalt come</hi> to it.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Later,</hi> the <hi>ſeaſonableneſſe</hi> of the arival; is ſet out two wayes,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Properly,</hi> in a <hi>full age.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Metaphorically,</hi> or by way of <hi>reſemblance, like as a ſhock of corn cometh in his ſeaſon.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. I begin with the former part, and therein with the <hi>firſt</hi> particular, the <hi>Port, or place</hi> it ſelf, to which even the godly muſt arive, The <hi>grave.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This hath been the place where the holieſt men have met,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer </seg>
               </label> and to which the deareſt Saints, the <hi>Jobs</hi> of God, have come. The grave (I ſay) is their term, their Center.<note place="margin">Gen. 25.8. 1 Kings 2.1. Zech. 1.5.</note> The holy Patriarchs of old, <hi>Abraham the friend of God.</hi> The godly Kings, <hi>David went the way of all fleſh.</hi> The <hi>Prophets live not for ever.</hi> The Apoſtles died; and thus it is
<list>
                  <item>In regard of
<list>
                        <item>1. <hi>Themſelves.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>Others.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Themſelves as they are
<list>
                        <item>1. <hi>Men.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>Sinfull men.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. <hi>Good men.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:115033:8"/>
            <p n="1">1. They are <hi>men.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Their bodies conſiſt of corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble principles, and are earthen veſſels and Cottage. Every day they daub them over (as it were) with food, and labour to keep them in reparations, and to make them tenantable for the ſoul, but alas all will not do, they cannot long be ſhord up, down they will at laſt and crumble to duſt. Even the props wherewith they are kept up, are but rotten, meats are corruptible,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Iſid Peluſ. l. <hi>1.</hi> ep. <hi>65.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>bread is cald that which periſheth.</hi> How can ſuch ſtructures, then, ſtand long? the truth is their falling begins (as <hi>Iſidore of Peluſium</hi> ſpeaks) with their very building; and being men they are ſubject alſo to the ſame acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, and caſualties with others.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Sinfull men.</hi> Tis true ſin is <hi>in</hi> them, and <hi>not</hi> in them: <hi>in</hi> them, not as their <hi>love</hi> but their <hi>load</hi> and vexation. And death doth befall them, and doth <hi>not</hi> befall. <hi>Doth</hi> befall them, as afflictive to ſenſe, as a cure of their woes, as a conſequent of ſin; but not as a curſe, or a wrathfull puniſhment; but yet this repeated addition <hi>(and he dyed)</hi> ſubjoyned to the relation of the long lives of the ancient Patriarchs, ſhewed the immoveable certainty of that threatning of death againſt <hi>Adams ſin,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the deceitfull promiſe of the devil.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They are <hi>holy</hi> men. And to the grave they muſt come. Firſt, For a <hi>reſiing</hi> place. Here is <hi>not their reſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7.24. Rom. 6.7. 2 Cor. 5.6.8. 1 Theſ. 4.16.</note> their <hi>works</hi> at length <hi>follow them,</hi> and they ſhall not follow their work any more. Secondly, They muſt be perfectly <hi>freed from ſin,</hi> which till death they cannot be. Thirdly, They muſt have their <hi>Crown</hi> of life; and Fourthly, Shall for ever be with the Lord, who loves his children ſo well, that he will not alwayes ſuffer them to be abroad, and abſent from him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In regard of <hi>others,</hi> they muſt come to the grave.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:115033:9"/>Firſt, Some are unkind and cruel to them, and haply they hurry them to the Port of the grave with a bluſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſtorm and tempeſt of perſecution. The Saints (eſpecially Miniſters) of Chriſt are ſet in the forlorn hope, and commonly the bullet ſooneſt hits them. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, Some idolize them, deifie them: how many, when adored, hath God grownde to pouder, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did the <hi>Iſraelites Calf,</hi> and removed them from men, when we have made them equall with God. Its the great ſin of the times either to deifie or nullifie men. God loves neither. Thirdly, The living muſt prize them, and get much good by them in a little time. He who hath a book lent him, but for a little while, makes the more haſt to read it over, the Prophets and Saints of God <hi>live not ever,</hi> nor are given us to uſe as long as we pleaſe, they are but lent us, and we muſt improve them ſpeedily. God hath held the candle of a Saints Life, and a Miniſters Doctrine to many idle profeſſors many a year, and he oft puts out this light to puniſh them for their negligence. Since then, even the beſt muſt come to the grave, let them ſtudy to do much for God while they live. The grave is a place of ſilence and reſt.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>The living, the living they praiſe</hi> and are employed for God. Short ſeaſons require ſpeedy ſervices. The near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of death ſhould put us upon holy ſerviceableneſſe during life, as for the preſerving of a ſweet and precious remembrance of our ſelves in that generation which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows ſo eſpecially for the tranſmitting by our examples, holineſs to Poſterity, that ſo a ſeed of Saints may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in the World, when we are dead and gone. And truely as otherwiſe we ſhall die while we live, ſo here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we ſhall live when we are dead, and be like civet, which, when tis taken out of the box, leaves a ſweet ſavour behind it.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:115033:9"/>
            <p n="2">2.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Let not any ſettle themſelves ſecurely in this World, he is a mad man, that will go about to build a houſe upon a quaking quag-mire, upon a rotten foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation. The longeſt lived of thoſe long-lived Patriarchs lived not a thouſand years; God hereby ſhewing that the longeſt life of any of the ſons of men is not able to reach to that ſpace which in reſpect of Gods Eternity is not a day. Expect not Eternity in this life.<note place="margin">Vid Rivet. in Gen.</note> Let us live as if we were alwayes dying, and yet as ſuch as are ever to live. Set not up your hopes, your expectations here; the grave will rub off all our worldly grandeur, as a narrow hole ſweepes off all the apples, that the fooliſh hedge-hog loads her prickles withall. Labour to be taken off from the world, before you are taken out of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly if <hi>Saints</hi> muſt <hi>come to the grave,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. Joh. 9.4, 12.35.</note> get good by them, while they live. Walk and work <hi>by the</hi> light <hi>while you have it with you.</hi> Neglect not to get good by the godly, in hope to enjoy them longer with you. Thou mayſt bewail thy over-ſlipt opportunities when tis too late. <hi>I will not let thee go except thou bleſſe me,</hi> you know it was the ſpeech of <hi>Jacob</hi> to God. O Lord, (ſay thou) let not not ſuch a Saint go, ſuch a Miniſter die, till thou haſt bleſſed me by his meanes, let not his light be put out, till he hath ſhewed me the way to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, better.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Fourthly if Saints muſt die, you that live,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> ſtand up in their ſtead, if God take away pillars, be not you as reeds. Supply their departure by your piety and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Laſtly muſt Saints die?<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> here is comfort in many reſpects; <hi>they</hi> ſhall come to the grave, <hi>they</hi> ſhall die, but their <hi>ſouls</hi> ſhall never die, the <hi>ſecond death hath no power over them;</hi> they ſhall die, but ſecondly the <hi>Church</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:115033:10"/>ſhall never die: they ſhall die, but thirdly their <hi>works</hi> ſhall never die, theſe ſhall <hi>follow them:</hi> they ſhall die, but fourthly, their God ſhall never die: the Prophets of God, <hi>Do they live for ever?</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> but the God of the Prophets lives for ever. Laſtly, they dye, and therefore why ſhould not we be willing to dye, to fare as they fare. Not onely the wicked but Saints dye. A godly man was the firſt who dyed. If death were not advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, it ſhould never be the lot of Gods beloved.</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. Branch of the firſt part.</note> This Port or place of the Saints, the <hi>Grave,</hi> affords us ſomewhat more for meditation. <hi>It is a mercy</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to have a houſe to hide the head of the living in, but to have a ſepulchre in which to hide the head of the dead.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>It is a mercy</hi> to have a <hi>grave.</hi> Great was <hi>Abrahams</hi> provident care to purchaſe a burying-place for his <hi>dead.</hi> God himſelf buried <hi>Moſes</hi> his dear ſervant: nor was the contention of the Angel about <hi>the body of Moſes,</hi> to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der its burial, but onely to forbid the Devil to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at it. When the Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> are recorded, their burials are alſo frequently mentioned; and thoſe of the higheſt merit were buried in the <hi>upper part of the ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chres of the ſons of David,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 32.33. Nor was it a ſmall judgement of God inflicted upon <hi>Baaſha</hi> and <hi>Jeza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel,</hi> to be buried in the bellies of Dogs:<note place="margin">Ier. 22 19.</note> Or upon <hi>Jehoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>akim,</hi> that he ſhould be buried with the <hi>burial of an Aſſe,</hi> contemptibly caſt into a ditch. Or upon the king of <hi>Babylon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 14.20.</note> that he ſhould not be <hi>joyned with the kings in bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial.</hi> Neither was that a ſlight imprecation,<note place="margin">Pſal. 63.11.</note> 
               <hi>Let them be a portion for Foxes.</hi> Nor a ſmall threatning, <hi>Jer.</hi> 14.16. That the <hi>people ſhould be caſt out into the ſtreets, and have none to bury them; and that the bones of the kings, &amp; prieſts, and prophets,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 8.2.</note> 
               <hi>ſhould be taken out of the grave, and laid open to the ſun and moon.</hi> Nor a ſmall complaint, that the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115033:10"/>
               <hi>enemies</hi> of the Church had given the dead <hi>bodies of Gods ſaints, to be meat to the fowls of the heaven, and their fleſh unto the beaſts of the earth.</hi> Want of burial is ſo hateful, that ſome have been more reſtrained from ſin by the fear of not being buried, then of dying. And <hi>David</hi> commends the burial of a dead <hi>Saul:</hi> nay <hi>Jehu</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands the burial of the remains of a curſed <hi>Jezabel.</hi> The practiſe (therefore) of giving the body decent bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial is very commendable Sutable it is, that the body,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> a piece of Gods workmanſhip ſo <hi>curiouſly wrought, Pſal.</hi> 139. ſhould not be careleſly thrown away. Yea, it hath been <hi>repair'd, redeem'd,</hi> as well as <hi>made</hi> by God. It is partner in redemption with the ſoul, and bought with the <hi>precious blood</hi> of Chriſt: The body is alſo ſanctified for the ſpirits <hi>temple.</hi> The ointment of ſanctification reſts not onely on the <hi>head</hi> (the ſoul) but runs down al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts not onely on the <hi>head</hi> (the ſoul) but runs down al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo upon the <hi>skirts,</hi> (the body.) The chair where the King of glory hath ſate ſhould not be abuſed. With the bodies of our deceaſed friends we lately had ſweet commerce; haply they were very beneficial to us. The body of a faithful Miniſter was an <hi>earthen</hi> Conduit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pipe whereby God conveighed ſpiritual comforts to our ſouls The body was once a partner with the ſoul in all her actions, it was the ſouls brother-twin; what could the ſoul do without it? whatever was in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding was conveighed by the <hi>ſence.</hi> The ſoul ſees by its eyes, hears by its ears, works by its hands; yea, which is more, there is an indiſſoluble union between the duſt in the <hi>grave,</hi> and the glorious ſoul. Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards are but <hi>ſleeping-places,</hi> and (as they were called a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Jews) <hi>houſes of the living.</hi> A great Heir is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, though he be for the preſent in rags: and which is more, our very bodies are the <hi>members of Chriſt,</hi> and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115033:11"/>of that lump, whereof he was the <hi>Firſt-fruits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence is diſcovered,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> the more then heatheniſh Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barouſneſſe of the Papiſts, both in denying and recal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling burial, digging up the dead again, as they dealt with the bodies of <hi>Paulus Fagius,</hi> and <hi>Peter Martyrs</hi> wife; Heathens themſelves have ſhewen greater humanity; witneſſe that of <hi>Alexander,</hi> in allowing enterment to the dead body of <hi>Darius, Hanibal</hi> to <hi>Marcellus</hi>'s, <hi>Caeſar</hi> to <hi>Pompey's.</hi> The comfort of Saints is, that God keeps <hi>every one of their bones;</hi> and that as he <hi>left not one out of his book,</hi> when he made them at firſt, ſo that neither ſhall one be miſſing when he will remake them. Nor is the <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> folly of Papiſts about the bodies of the dead, leſſe reproveable then their <hi>inhumane cruelty,</hi> I mean, their religious reverencing of the reliques of the deceaſed. Though the Devil could not obtain a <hi>licenſe</hi> for this ſin (according to ſome) from <hi>Michael,</hi> yet hath he obtained a <hi>command</hi> for it from the <hi>Pope.</hi> To <hi>name</hi> this practiſe is to <hi>confute</hi> it. Its <hi>idolatry,</hi> derogation from the merits of Chriſt, <hi>ridiculouſneſſe,</hi> (for Popiſh Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians tell us, that the bones of the worſhip'd have after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward proved to be the reliques of theeves and murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers &amp; to ſuch a proportion are they increaſed, that they are rather the objects of deriſion then adoration.) Yea laſtly, its <hi>injuriouſneſſe</hi> to the ſaints, who in pretence are honoured (whoſe bodies hereby have <hi>inſepultam ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam</hi> are kept from their honour of reſt, and brought into a condition threatned as a curſe) are more then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to procure our abhorrence of it. To conclude this; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> the care (yet) of a dead <hi>body</hi> ſhould not be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable to that of the <hi>living, ever-living ſoul:</hi> what profit is it for the body to be embalmed, and entombed richly, and the ſoul to be tormented eternally? As great
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115033:11"/>a folly is the reſpecting of the <hi>vile body,</hi> joyn'd with the neglecting of the <hi>precious ſoul,</hi> as for a frantick mother <hi>onely</hi> to lament the loſſe of the coat of her drowned childe, never laying to heart the loſſe of the childe it ſelf. Chiefly look after thy ſoul and God will take care of thy body, it ſhall be embalmed to eternity, though it ſhould be eaten up with the beaſts of the earth.</p>
            <p>This for the <hi>firſt,</hi> the Saints <hi>Port</hi> or <hi>Place,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond particular in the firſt part of the Text.</note> the <hi>Grave</hi> But ſecondly, what <hi>kinde of paſſage</hi> ſhall he have thither? <hi>Eliphaz</hi> ſaith, <hi>He ſhall come to the grave:</hi> And this notes that his paſſage to the grave ſhall be <hi>willing,</hi> and <hi>uninfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</hi> He ſhall get thither by <hi>coming,</hi> he ſhall go, as it were upon his <hi>own feet,</hi> he ſhall not be hailed and drag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and pulled thither againſt his own minde.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>3</label> It ſhall be his portion to be <hi>willing to dye;</hi> his ſoul ſhall not be <hi>required</hi> of him, taken from him by force againſt his wil, as his was <hi>Luke</hi> 12.20. No, he ſhall be one, that is pleaſed with the thoughts of his departure, and <hi>deſires with Paul to be diſſolved.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 19.4.</note> One that may ſay (as <hi>Elijah,</hi>) <hi>Lord take away my ſoul;</hi> and with <hi>Simeon, Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 2.29.</note> 
               <hi>now letteſt thou thy ſervant depart:</hi> He will open the door cheerfully, when his maſter ſhall but ſend his Sergeant Death to knock; he will meet Death (as it were) half way, Death ſhall be his <hi>priviledge</hi> as well as his task; with <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> he <hi>running</hi> to the ſepulchre, not being urged, drag'd to it <hi>Neceſſitatis <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>inculo,</hi> by the bond of neceſſity, but making toward it <hi>Voluntatis Obſequio,</hi> with the holy forwardneſſe of his will. <hi>Thou ſhalt come.</hi> By death Saints are freed, from the <hi>reach of,</hi> as well as hurt <hi>by Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans temptations:</hi> From the evil company of the ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, from divine deſertion, from the burden of ſin and corruption, from the painful and laborious employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their places, from all bodily infirmities and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115033:12"/>diſeaſes (death is the beſt phyſick,) from all Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlike chaſtiſements,<note place="margin">Minus pie vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis, ſi minus perſecutionem pertuleris. Gr. ep. <hi>27.</hi> l. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> from an unkinde, perſecuting unquiet world (that bed of thorns) they love not the world, and therefore they linger not in it. They are in love with heaven, where they ſhall have the conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of grace and glory, and enjoy the ſweet ſoul-raviſhing ſociety of their Friend, Huſband, Saviour, Head; and therefore as their better <hi>portion</hi> Chriſt, ſo their better <hi>part</hi> their <hi>heart,</hi> is there already. He hath perfumed the grave for them, and made that narrow noiſome place, a place of eaſe and ſweetneſſe. Ever ſince Chriſt trod and walk'd upon the ſea of death, they may ſay (as <hi>Peter</hi> to Chriſt) <hi>Lord, if it be thou, bid me come unto thee on the water.</hi> Chriſt by his death hath <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured,</hi> and they when they dye, do but <hi>enter into his labours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word: Sin the ſtrength and only weapon which Death can uſe, is by the merit and ſpirit of Chriſt, taken away; ſo that death is now become a ſtingleſſe Serpent, and a toothleſſe Lion; a tame, diſarmed enemy, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the bare name and notion of an enemy. The un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingneſſe of Gods people to dye, is not becauſe they judge that death is not good for <hi>them,</hi> but becauſe they think not themſelves good enough for <hi>death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How unlike to Chriſtians,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>1</label> do they then ſhew themſelves who are ſo loath to dye, that they will not <hi>come,</hi> but muſt be <hi>drag'd</hi> to the <hi>grave,</hi> yea, to the very <hi>thoughts</hi> thereof, who though they cannot live without miſery, yet neither can they be content with that, which as they cannot avoid, ſo will put an end to all miſery. Oh how unſuitable is this diſtemper, to thoſe who both profeſs they deſire that Gods will may be done, &amp; that they are <hi>pilgrims and ſtrangers upon earth,</hi> and that heaven is their countrey, their fathers houſe!</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:115033:12"/>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>How excellent is the grace of Faith,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> which makes a beleever cheerfully to come to that, to which another muſt be drawn and dragd, I mean the grave! To a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever, when his faith is on the wing, life (as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of his) <hi>is not dear,</hi> and death (as he ſpeaks of his) is deſired.<note place="margin">Acts 20.24. Phil. 1.22.23.</note> It was as hard to make <hi>Paul</hi> patient when he thought of <hi>living,</hi> as to make another patient when he expected <hi>dying.</hi> Faith is the alone mantle which divides the waters of death: ſo as that a beleever ſees he may go through them dry-ſhod. That grace which throwes the Croſſe of Chriſt into theſe waters of <hi>marah,</hi> and thereby makes them not onely wholſome but plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Its our duty to labour for ſuch a ſpirit,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> as to be willing to die: to <hi>Come to the grave.</hi> If it was Chriſts deſire to <hi>die for us,</hi> ſhould it not be our longing to <hi>live with him.</hi> To this end, Firſt, <hi>clear up thy intereſt</hi> in Chriſts death, the death of thy death: the blood of Chriſt makes pale death look beautifully. He was a <hi>curſe,</hi> and death is thereby a <hi>bleſſing:</hi> this <hi>horn of ſalvation</hi> dipt into the waters of death, makes them not onely <hi>poiſonleſs</hi> but <hi>wholſome:</hi> death hath left its ſting in the ſides of Chriſt. <hi>He that beleeveth in him, ſhall never die.</hi> Secondly, In looking <hi>toward</hi> death, look likewiſe <hi>beyond</hi> it: even as far, as the benefits which follow it: view that bleſſedneſſe which is <hi>inviſible.</hi> Conſider not death as it ſhews it ſelf to an <hi>eye of ſence,</hi> but as its manifeſt to an <hi>eye of Faith,</hi> not as an enemie to man, but as changed by Chriſt into a friend, yea the beſt friend, next Chriſt himſelf. Thirdly, Oft <hi>meditate of death:</hi> let it not ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize thee unawares: let it be an acquaintance not a a ſtranger: die before thou dieſt: death onely ſeems a great buſineſſe, to thoſe who are to go through it all at
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115033:13"/>once. Fourthly, <hi>Hate ſin:</hi> the love of ſin makes men fear death; and he who hates ſin muſt needs love death, becauſe thereby ſin ſhall be wholly aboliſht. The love of ſin is the <hi>arming of death,</hi> and an armed enemy muſt needs be formidable, Fifthly, <hi>Wean thy ſelf from the world:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Omnia iſta no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis accedant ut ſine ulla noſtra lacera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione diſcedant Sen. ep. <hi>74.</hi>
               </note> an empty traveller, will ſing when he meets with the thief; he who looks upon himſelf as poſſeſſing nothing in the world, fears not a ſtripping by death: let not the world cleave to thee, as a ſhirt which ſticks to an ulcerous body, and ſo pulls skin and fleſh away with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. The looſe tooth comes out with eaſe, but when it ſtands faſt in the head its drawn out with much pain. If the world and our affections be faſtned, the parting will not be without much difficulty.</p>
            <p>I come to the <hi>ſecond part of the text,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Generall part of the Text.</note> and that is the ſeaſonableneſs of a Saints coming to the grave: and</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is ſet out properly. <hi>In a full age. Tremelius</hi> renders it, <hi>cum ſenio, with old age, Pagnine in maturitate,</hi> in <hi>ripeneſſe. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>atablus</hi> in <hi>ſenio.</hi> The <hi>uulgar</hi> latine in <hi>abundantia,</hi> in <hi>abundance,</hi> which ſome expound of <hi>abundance of honours</hi> and riches, others of abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of years and long life; and indeed the Hebrew word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſignifies <hi>old age,</hi> or <hi>a full age</hi> which ſtands in the abundance of <hi>years:</hi> and therefore I know no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why we ſhould by giving other interpretations, raiſe a duſt to obſcure the ſence. But yet withall here is imported a happy, bleſſed old age, ſuch an old age as is a <hi>promiſe,</hi> and is in ſcripture frequently cal'd a <hi>good old age,</hi> and therefore this <hi>full age</hi> may include a <hi>threefold fulneſſe</hi> (to name no more.)<note place="margin">1. <hi>Maturitas civilis.</hi> Gen. 15.15. 1 Chro. 29.28</note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, a <hi>Civill fulneſſe,</hi> or maturity, and ſo <hi>a full age</hi> is an age full of <hi>honour,</hi> peace, and riches, ſo it is ſaid, that <hi>David died in a good old age, full of dayes, riches and honour,</hi> this civil fulneſſe being not onely conſidered
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115033:13"/>
               <hi>actively</hi> when men have ſet their houſes in order, ſetled their Eſtates, when they are ripe, and fit, for death, in regard, they have made their will, and fitly diſpoſed of their goods (the neglect whereof for fear of death, being a childiſh folly, for death is never awhit the nearer, becauſe we place it before our eyes nor the further off, becauſe we will not ſee it:) but <hi>paſſively</hi> alſo, when God hath beſtowed upon men a full eſtate, and eſpecially a good name, when they go not out in a ſnuff of diſgrace, and the ſun of their life, ſets not in a cloud, but they are buried <hi>with honour,</hi> and leave a ſweetly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumed memoriall behind them, their name living when their bodies are dead. In this reſpect <hi>Jeroboams</hi> ſon died in a <hi>full age,</hi> being honoured with the lamentations of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>Jehojada</hi> who was buried honourably in the <hi>chief of the Sepulchers of the Kings of Judah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, here may be recomprehended a <hi>Religious fulneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Maturitas ſpiritualis.</note> and that in three reſpects.</p>
            <p>Firſt, when a perſon is <hi>born again,</hi> hath gotten grace into his ſoul, and an intereſt in Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>of whoſe fulneſſe he hath received and grace for grace,</hi> John 1.16. whereby he hath a meekneſs to die: and thus yong ones may be of <hi>full age</hi> even before they are one and twenty, they may be old young-men; as on the contrary; old ſinners, or ſinners though of an hundred year old, may be cal'd young or childiſh old-men: young <hi>Joſiah had</hi> his <hi>full age,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aetas immatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, pijs matura<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſt, et plus illis eſt annos decem vixiſſe, quam inpijs centum. inercer. in loc.</note> in this reſpect, before he died, and (as <hi>Mercer</hi> well notes on the text) <hi>a green age</hi> is to the godly <hi>a ripe age,</hi> and they live more in ten years, then the wicked, in an hundred.</p>
            <p>Secondly, when a perſon not onely hath grace, but alſo is <hi>beneficial,</hi> uſefull, doth much good in his time, is <hi>diffuſive</hi> of holineſſe, <hi>full of good works, ſerves his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115033:14"/>generation,</hi> and hath done <hi>his work,</hi> before he fals <hi>a ſleep,</hi> hath his <hi>Dorcaſſes</hi> coats to be ſeen after his death; it is only our <hi>doing good</hi> that makes us called <hi>good,</hi> we are not called good men, for the good, which we have <hi>within us,</hi> but for the good that is performed <hi>by us;</hi> that bleſſed <hi>Hilarion</hi> died in a good age in a <hi>full age</hi> who having ſerved Jeſus Chriſt ſeventy years, when he came to die ſaid, Go forth O foul. In this ſence <hi>Elijah</hi> ſaith, according to ſome) it <hi>is enough.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 65.20.</note> Unlike to others who are <hi>infants of dayes,</hi> that have not filled their dayes, which are like emptie, white paper, having nothing written in them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, when a perſon <hi>is ſatisfied, and contented</hi> with that time, and age which God hath already given him, and is (as the Scripture oft expreſſeth it) <hi>full of dayes,</hi> having lived as long as himſelf deſired, or as heart could wiſh, accounting (as <hi>Elijah</hi> ſpeaks) that he hath lived <hi>enough.</hi> Thus <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 25.8. <hi>Iſaac,</hi> Gen. 35.29. <hi>David,</hi> 1 Chro. 23.1. <hi>Job</hi> chap. 42.17. <hi>Jehoiada,</hi> 2 Chro. 24.15. are all ſaid to be <hi>full of dayes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rarus qui exacto con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentus tempore vitae, cedat, uti conuiua ſatur. Hor. ſat. <hi>1.</hi> Omnino rerum ſum ſatur prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentium.</note> to them there was not ſo much an irkſome tediouſneſſe, as a fulneſſe and ſatiety of life: they were as willing to leave this world, as men are wont to be to riſe from the table when they have eaten their fill. It was an expreſſion ſutable to a godly man when he ſaid; <hi>Lord I am cloyd with theſe preſent en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments</hi> (for indeed they <hi>cloy us,</hi> but they do not <hi>ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie us</hi>) there is the ſecond, <hi>a fulneſſe of age,</hi> in regard of a <hi>Religious fulneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Maturitas Naturalis.</note> there is a fulneſſe of age in regard of a <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall fulneſſe,</hi> which is the fulneſſe here <hi>principally</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, (though the other be not excluded) and this naturall fulneſſe of age is twofold. Firſt, here is intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>ſenectus ſera a late, long, ripe age,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Senectus ſera.</note> in reſpect of the great number of its years; he ſhall not be taken away
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115033:14"/>by an immature, untimely death, when he hath lived out but <hi>half his dayes,</hi> the candle of his life ſhall not be blown out, no, this lamp ſhall not be <hi>put</hi> but <hi>go out;</hi> all the oyl ſhall be ſpent, his vital moiſture ſhal be dried up, &amp; gone. In a word: He ſhall not be taken away in the <hi>midſt of his dayes.</hi> There is a prediction, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 55.23. that the wicked ſhall not <hi>Dimidiare dies, half their dayes;</hi>
               <note place="margin">juxta editio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem vulgata.</note> 
               <hi>i. e.</hi> live out half thoſe dayes, which according to the courſe of nature they might reach unto. But <hi>Eliphaz</hi> here intends that <hi>Job</hi> ſhall go, though <hi>ſurely,</hi> yet <hi>ſlowly</hi> to heaven, and ſhall not be as the corn <hi>upon the houſe top, that wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hers, before it be grown up,</hi> but ſhall come to his full meaſure of yeers, and live as long as (according to the courſe of nature) could be expected.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In this natural fulneſſe is contained <hi>Senectus ſana,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Senectus ſana vegeta.</note> an <hi>hail, youthful old-age,</hi> ſound, ſtrong, vigorous, and that both in reſpect of <hi>body</hi> and <hi>minde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Of <hi>body.</hi> When men are free, for the moſt part from ſuch bodily infirmities, and annoiances as old age is wont to be infeſted withal, and are without, though not ſuch weakneſſe as neceſſarily accompnaies the decay of nature, yet ſuch pains, aches, and diſeaſes, as are wont to annoy that age. Health is a mercy at all times, even ſuch wherin others are wont uſually to <hi>enjoy</hi> it; but eſpecially is it a bleſſing to enjoy it in that age, wherein men moſt commonly <hi>want it.</hi> Health in infectious times is a ſingular mercy, and ſo is it in old-age which is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to ſo many diſeaſes. It is not ſo much the decay of bodily ſtrength, as pains and diſeaſes, which make old age burdenſome. How choice a priviledge is it to be fat and flouriſhing even in old age, (as it is ſpoken in another regard, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 92.14.) not altogether unlike to <hi>Moſes,</hi> who being an hundred and twenty yeers
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115033:15"/>old when he died, <hi>his eye was not dim, nor his natural ſtrength abated, Deut.</hi> 34.7. Or <hi>Caleb,</hi> who <hi>Joſh.</hi> 14.11. ſaith of himſelf, that he was as ſtrong as eighty five yeers as he was at fourty, for war. Here was <hi>a Spring in Autumn,</hi> a good healthful old age, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: not an old age, ſick, diſeaſed, ſqualid: the bones (here) are not full of the <hi>ſins of youth</hi> in regard whereof there are ſome men older at <hi>thirty,</hi> then others are at <hi>ſixty:</hi> they are old, when they are <hi>young.</hi> in regard of the diſeaſes, they have brought upon themſelves by their intemperance.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Of <hi>minde.</hi> When men are not (though old in yeers) crazy in their intellectuals, but the parts of their minde are green and youthful, they being not (as ſome) <hi>twice children:</hi> a great bleſſing it is for young men to have the parts of old men in regard of <hi>prudence;</hi> and for <hi>old men</hi> to retain their youthful and pregnant abilities of knowledge, fancy, memory, apprehenſion; and the <hi>eyes of their minde</hi> not to grow dim and dark with old age. Thus this ſeaſon of coming <hi>of the grave,</hi> is ſet forth properly, in <hi>a full age.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2 2. Branch of the 2. Part of the Text opened.</note> Secondly, it is deſcribed <hi>metaphorically</hi> in theſe words, <hi>Like as a ſhock of corn cometh in, in his ſeaſon.</hi> Theſe words <hi>A ſhock of corn,</hi> may as well be rendred <hi>A heap of corn,</hi> the word ſignifies both; either corn before or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter its <hi>threſhing.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> This corn is ſaid to <hi>come in.</hi> The word in the Original imports <hi>to aſcend:</hi> and corn may be ſaid to <hi>aſcend</hi> by bringing, carrying, laying of it up, and it comes in <hi>in its ſeaſon,</hi> when it comes in, in its full <hi>matu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> and perfect <hi>ripeneſſe:</hi> and ſo a Saint ſhall come to his grave, in a mature age, like unto a ſhock of corn in its <hi>ſeaſon</hi> and <hi>ripeneſſe.</hi> But why is a <hi>full age</hi> compared unto the fully mature and <hi>ripened corn?</hi> In ſundry re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:115033:15"/>
            <p n="1">1.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt in reagard of the <hi>variety of ſeaſons</hi> that ripened corn muſt go through, before it be ripe. There muſt be ſtorms, bluſtering windes, nipping froſts, ſun-ſhine, &amp; rain, go over it, before it come to maturity; and the froſt is as good to kill the worms, as the ſun is needfull to quicken its growth: and who is there hath-hath lived to a full ripe age, that is not as ripe corn in this reſpect; witneſſe <hi>Jacob Joſeph, David, Paul,</hi> &amp;c. When man of yeers, but hath been a man of variety of conditions in the world, but hath met with his ſtormes and windes, with his unkinde uſage, and a troubleſome ſtate here below? And its good it ſhould be ſo; we ſhould not be willing to be cut down by the <hi>ſickle</hi> of death, nor long to be taken into the <hi>barn,</hi> (laid up in the quiet grave) were not the field ſtormy and rainy, the world boiſterous and unquiet. The world is too much loved now when it is troubleſome; oh how much deſired would it be were it altogether delightful!</p>
            <p n="2">2.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, a <hi>full age</hi> is as a ripe <hi>ſhock of corn</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the <hi>diverſity</hi> of ages, and periods of a mans life.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt the corn is <hi>ſown</hi> in the ground, ſo the ſeed is <hi>thrown</hi> into the womb.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, the <hi>corn</hi> doth <hi>Herbeſcere,</hi> it is green in the tender <hi>blade,</hi> and grows like an herb, and this is as our <hi>childhood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, the corn doth grow to a <hi>ſtalk;</hi> it doth <hi>adoleſcere</hi> grow and ſhoot up to ſome kinde of <hi>ſtature,</hi> and this is our <hi>youthful</hi> age.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Fourthly, there is a <hi>full ear</hi> afterward, and that is in the <hi>manhood,</hi> when a man is come to ſome fulneſſe of abilities, and endowments to tranſact his calling, to go through his duties, and employments.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Fifthly, there is a <hi>maturity,</hi> the corn comes to be ripe, ſear, dry, and this is <hi>old age.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:115033:16"/>
            <p>Sixthly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> there is the <hi>cutting down</hi> of the corn, and this is by the <hi>ſickle of death</hi> as this godly man once ſaid the <hi>ſickle of death will cut down all my diſeaſes,</hi> and pains <hi>and troubles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seventhly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> after it is cut down it is laid up in the <hi>born:</hi> when we are cut down by death, we are put into our grave, that is our <hi>barn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eightly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> when it is put into the barn, then it is <hi>threſhed</hi> and fanned; there will come a day of Judgement where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there ſhall be a diſquiſition, a ſifting, and fanning, of all the actions, that have been done ini the World.</p>
            <p>Ninthly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> it is ſet before the Maſter, upon his table for his uſe: the people of God ſhall be preſented before <hi>the preſence of glory,</hi> they ſhall be <hi>Shew-bread</hi> in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; they are <hi>for</hi> God, and ſhall be <hi>with</hi> God, for ever, I am (ſaid <hi>Ignatius</hi>) to be grownd with the teeth of the <hi>wild beaſts,</hi> that ſo I may be as manchet, fine bread for my Maſter.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> a <hi>full age</hi> is as <hi>ripe Corn,</hi> in regard of the coſt that is beſtowed upon corn, before it comes to <hi>maturi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> how much labour is laid out! how much pains do men take to raiſe the expectation of an harveſt! How much plowing, harrowing, dunging, weeding doth corn require before it be carried in! and it may be, that though it hath been a yeer or two in the fitting and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring for a crop, its cut down by 2. or 3. harveſt men in a day or two. A Parent hath laid out a great deal of coſt, it may be in the Educating of a Child, in the Univerſity, bringing him up in the Arts, nurturing him and poliſhing him with choiſeſt Education, and then death comes, and cuts him down with his ſickle in a few houres; when a man is full of wind and ſwoln with gifts and knowledge, death comes with a little prick (as it
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115033:16"/>were) of a pin, and lets out all the wind again, and all mans <hi>thoughts periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> maturity of age is like the maturity of corn in regard of <hi>hopefulneſſe;</hi> the husband-man <hi>ſowes in hope,</hi> every one expects a harveſt, if he hath had a ſeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time: old age is that which men both covet and expect. If Satan and ſecurity be a mans teachers, he will ſay, I ſhall live long enough, let the Miniſters, and examples of mortality ſay what they will. No man is ſo old but he hopes to live one yeer longer; and the youngeſt hopes to live to old age.</p>
            <p>Fifthly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> a <hi>full age</hi> is like unto <hi>ripe corn,</hi> in regard of <hi>continuation.</hi> No tooth nor foot of the beaſt hath cropt or trod it down. All the blaſts that have befallen it, all the ſtorms that have bin caſt upon it, may make it bend, but yet till the harveſt comes, it is not cut down and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed utterly: thus it is, here, till God take us away by death, till our time is come, nothing ſhall take us away, when that is come preſently we are gone; our times are not in our enemies hand, for if ſo, we ſhould not live long enough, they are not in our own hands, if they were, we ſhould live too long, but they are in Gods hands, <hi>my times</hi> (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) <hi>are in thy hands,</hi> Pſal. 31.15.</p>
            <p>Sixthly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
               <hi>a full age</hi> is compared to <hi>ripe</hi> corn in regard of <hi>fitneſſe for the barn,</hi> and for the maſters uſe, <hi>ripe</hi> corn is onely <hi>acceptable</hi> corn, onely good corn, onely ſuch as pleaſeth the tooth of the feeder; they that are ripe in yeers, ſhould be ripe in grace; they that are <hi>full of dayes</hi> ſhould be full of <hi>Holineſſe;</hi> they ſhould be fit for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; if any, they that have one foot in the grave ſhould have the other in Heaven; they that have white heads ſhould not (as the ſwan which under her white feathers
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115033:17"/>hath a black skin) have a black heart. In a word (we ſay) toward harveſt, corn ripens night and day, (it is a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try proverb:) when a man growes old, he ſhouldl grow Heavenward might and day. Oh he ſhould live more in one day then heretofore he hath done in a whole yeer.</p>
            <p>A <hi>full age</hi> is as <hi>ripe corn,</hi> in regard of the <hi>certainty of harvest,</hi> and cutting down: The corn which hath ſtood longeſt, meets at laſt with a ſickle: they that have lived longeſt muſt die at length, and be cut down with deaths ſickle; the longeſt Summers day, hath a Sun ſet; though thy age be a Summers age, yet it muſt end. Its poſſible, corn may be troden down and devoured by the beaſts of the field, withered with ſcorching heat, or deſtroyed with floods, but ſhould it eſcape all thoſe dangers, to be ſure, it muſt meet with a ſickle at the harveſt. Though a man eſcape a violent death, and the many diſeaſes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to youth and manhood, at length he muſt have a diſeaſe, whereby he muſt die. A <hi>Neſtors</hi> a <hi>Methuſalems</hi> age muſt end. The ſailes of our <hi>Times</hi> as well as of <hi>Time,</hi> are daily <hi>winding up:</hi> unto all the deſcriptions of the great age of the Patriarchs before the flood, its added, <hi>and he died.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. Laſtly, a <hi>full age</hi> is as ripe corn, in reſpect of the near approach of its cutting down: ripe corn hath not long to ſtand; the young-<hi>may,</hi> the old <hi>muſt dîe. How long have I to live</hi> (ſaid old <hi>Barzillai</hi>) that I ſhould go up with the King? Grey hairs are deaths harbingers, which with their white ſtrokes, mark and take up lodgings for death, <hi>the King of terrours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus! I have opened both the branches of this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of my Text: the former ſetting form the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of a Saints coming to the grave, <hi>properly,</hi> the ſecond <hi>Metaphorically.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:115033:17"/>
            <p>The uſe that I ſhall make of this ſecond Part in both its branches, <hi>put together</hi> ſhall be <hi>two-fold.</hi> I ſhall apply what I have ſaid.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To our <hi>ſelves.</hi> 2. To <hi>the occaſion.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt, there are then theſe following in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences that I draw from hence, if (as I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed unto you) a <hi>full age</hi> be here promiſed, and ſuch as is like unto <hi>ripe corn;</hi> I Note then in the firſt place, <hi>The difference between godly and wicked men.</hi> The godly mans age is a <hi>full age</hi> to him, he is fill'd with age, and hath a ſatiety of life; Its far otherwiſe with the wicked. I read not of any one of them in Scripture of whom its ſaid, that he was <hi>full of dayes</hi> none can be full of <hi>Time,</hi> but he who hath had a taſte of <hi>Eternity:</hi> the wicked never think they have enough either of the wealth or life of this World. By their good will they would never die. The miſeries and calamities of this world ſometimes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed may make them impatiently weary of their lives; But the godly in the midſt of all their worldly ſolaces and enjoyments, health, honour, wealth, &amp;c. are fill'd with dayes.<note place="margin">Gen 46.30.</note> 
               <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaid <hi>now let me die,</hi> when he was in the midſt of his greateſt worldly rejoycing by the unexpected mercy of ſeeing both <hi>Joſeph</hi> and his ſons. <hi>David</hi> was <hi>full of dayes</hi> when he was alſo <hi>full of riches and honour.</hi> The wicked may be angry with the troubles of <hi>this;</hi> but a Saint is enamoured with the Beauty of the <hi>next</hi> life, a wicked man may be weary of life, but a Saint is alſo deſirous <hi>of death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I obſerve,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nfulneſs of ſhortning our lives;</hi> a <hi>full age</hi> is a bleſſing <hi>promiſed,</hi> yea a choice bleſſing, firſt, then thoſe cowards are hence worthily reproved who ſhorten their lives <hi>by Duels</hi> the greateſt cowards in the World, who being purſu'd with a diſgrace, will run as far as hell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115033:18"/>they look back. Secondly, thoſe that ſhorten their lives by <hi>intemperance</hi> that <hi>dig their graves with their teeth,</hi> that are <hi>felons of themſelves,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Laſcivis bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis eſt aetas &amp; rara ſenectus.</note> that ſwallow, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their eſtates and lively-hoods, but their lives alſo down their throats: theſe (I ſay) unkindly prevent this kinde and ſweet enjoyment here promiſed, <hi>a full age;</hi> they being grown old by diſeaſes, before their time, making their tumors, rheums, and other diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers to prevent their old age, to be ſure the vigour and vivacity of it. Theſe do that againſt themſelves, which the very Devils deſired to ſhun, they tormenting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>before their time.</hi> Luxury is the greateſt enemy of health, and hinderance of old age. How many by being caſt away in the ſurges of riot and drunkenneſs, fall ſhort of the Port of a <hi>full age?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, great is the ſin of deriding at <hi>old age,</hi> and contempt of <hi>old men</hi> in their <hi>full age,</hi> as when men voice them <hi>twice children,</hi> ſilly men, Dotards; theſe ſcoffers imitating thoſe children that called the Propeht <hi>bald<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate.</hi> I remember a ſmart and fit anſwer which an old man once gave to a ſcoffing youngſter; the young man telling the old, that his memory grew weak and frail; well (replyed the old man.) <hi>though my memory be now f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ail, yet know: that I have forgotten more then ever thou didſt remember.</hi> If he that <hi>mocketh the poor,</hi> certainly he that deſpiſeth <hi>the aged, reproach th his Maker.</hi> The aged muſt be both honourable,<note place="margin">Prov. 17.5. Lev. 19.2.</note> and honoured, before whom thou muſt <hi>riſe up.</hi> They who will not honour old Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſeldom find their <hi>dayes</hi> to be <hi>long in the land which God gives them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Fourthly,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>4</label> I note from hence, That <hi>all the creatures ſhould not onely be improved ſpiritually, but particularly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, even to the putting of us in minde of death:</hi> even
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115033:18"/>the <hi>ſhocks</hi> of ripe <hi>corn,</hi> the ripe <hi>wheat</hi> that is in the field, ſhould make thee conſider, that as that ſame corn muſt ſhortly be carried into the Barn, ſo thou muſt be tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled into the grave; thy ſleep ſhould make thee think of the ſleep of death; the Autumn ſhould put thee in minde of the day of thy fading, falling leaf: the ſetting of the Sun, ſhould make thee forecaſt the ſetting of the ſun of thy life, the harveſt ſhould make thee think of deaths reaping ſickle, the dead creatures upon which thou daily feedeſt, ſhould convince thee that the feeder cannot live alwayes; the putting off thy clothes from thy body, ſhould inſtruct thee, of putting off (ſhortly) the clothes of thy body. The blood of the grape that thou drinkeſt, was preſſed and ſhed, before thou couldſt come to the ſweetneſſe of it. The skins which clothe us were the caſt ſutes of dead beaſts. When thou putteſt on thy clothes in the morning, thou ſhouldſt think of being clothed with new robes of the reſurrection. Oh could you do thus, you would not onely think of, but expect death in all places, as death expects you every where: Death may lie under your trencher, may be at the bottom of every cup. The delights of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſhould not extinguiſh the ſuggeſtions which they give us of mortality. The Ancients had their ſepulchres in their places of pleaſure, their Gardens: and (of old) ſome were wont to roll a dead-mans skil upon their table, after their greateſt feaſts.</p>
            <p n="5">5.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>5</label> Fifthly, note that <hi>old age is a bleſſing.</hi> 1. A <hi>full age,</hi> like unto the ripe corn is here <hi>promiſed,</hi> as an encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to duty, and the contrary is <hi>threatned</hi> as a curſe. God foretels that there ſhould not be an <hi>old man in the houſe of Eli.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 15.15. 1 Sam 2.32. Pſal. 55.22.</note> Its the curſe threatned againſt the wicked, <hi>that they ſhall not live out half their dayes,</hi> and be
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115033:19"/>like the <hi>corn on the houſe top, which withers before it be grown.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, it is <hi>laboured and contended for,</hi> as a great bleſſing; they that deſpiſe it, yet deſire it and would count it a mercy. All thy food is taken but to patch up thy cottage, that ſo thou mayeſt live till thou art an old man: Phyſicians are but Pilots to conduct to the haven of old age. All the phyſick that the Apothecary pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares; all the Phyſitians preſcriptions are but helps to old age; beyond old age thou canſt not go, to old age thou wouldſt fain go.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Grace is not onely an honour to old age, (as it is indeed to every age,) <hi>But old age is a great honour alſo to grace;</hi> they caſt a mutual luſtre upon one another. The oldeſt preſons moſt commend grace in <hi>having,</hi> becauſe in <hi>keeping</hi> it; grace <hi>beautifies</hi> the <hi>youngeſt,</hi> but it is not <hi>beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified</hi> ſo much by any as by the <hi>oldeſt.</hi> Theſe ſhew that after all the ſolicitations of ſin and vanity, grace is (yet) the <hi>beſt,</hi> and their beſt <hi>beloved,</hi> and that though they have ſerved <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> ſo many ſcores of yeers, yet that they eſteem him the beſt maſter, and are not weary of his ſervice, but that they account it impoſſible to change it for the beſt of temporals, unleſſe to loſſe. O how glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious is it, when there is the ſilver crown of gray hairs, and the golden crown of grace upon one head! How amiable a conjunction are the <hi>golden apples</hi> of grace in the <hi>ſilver picture</hi> of the hoary head!</p>
            <p n="4">4. Fourthly, its an age of the greateſt growth and perfection of grace, the bringing of our graces to the greateſt fulneſſe in this world. Old men (if godly) are ſpiritual hoarders; they have been laying up of grace all their dayes, and <hi>adding grace to grace,</hi> day after day, and yeer after yeer; ſermon after ſermon, ordinance
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115033:19"/>after ordinance: and a great many littles have by this time made a mickle. And how comfortable is it for a godly old man to recollect, that he hath not onely got much grace throughout his long life to <hi>himſelf,</hi> but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentally beſtowed much grace upon others: <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens children are the crown of old age</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>Pro.</hi> 17.6. but no children are ſo glorious golden, and gliſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a crown, as thoſe who are ſpiritual. Oh how hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py is it for a godly old man to be able to ſay, Lord, I am not onely my ſelf thy childe, but I have brought forth children to Jeſus Chriſt throughout my life, and who (now) are come to a great number.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Fifthly, it is in ſome reſpect the moſt advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous time of doing good:<note place="margin">Levit. 19.32. Dan. 7.13. Prov. 16.31. Prov. 20.29.</note> its an honourable age, (as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage) <hi>honourable among all men;</hi> a kinde of reſemblance of Gods antiquity who is called the <hi>ancient of dayes.</hi> The gray head is called beauty, and a <hi>crown of glory.</hi> Now as our duty to do good, ſo our opportunity of doing it to others, follows our receiving or honour from others. Beſides, old age brings <hi>wiſdom</hi> and <hi>experience,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore makes men more able to give wiſe and wholeſome counſel to others. It was a good expreſſion of him who call'd an old mans head the <hi>houſe of wiſdom.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Domicilium ſapientiae. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Clem. Paed. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Seris venit uſus ab annis. <hi>Ovid.</hi> Met. l. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> The moſt prudent Roman Convention, the <hi>Senate,</hi> was ſo called from <hi>old age;</hi> noting, that wiſdom is commonly the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowment of old men. The raſh and fooliſh counſellors of <hi>Rehoboam</hi> were young men. Old men are ſometime as eminent for <hi>wiſdom,</hi> as young men are for <hi>ſtrength.</hi> And its as rare to ſee a young man <hi>prudent,</hi> as an old man <hi>ſtrong.</hi> By grave and good counſel and advice, the ſtrength of the head, the aged may be more helpful, then the yonger may be by their hands. A few gray hairs may be more worth, then many yong locks, and green heads.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115033:20"/>The night is the beſt time for counſell, and ſo it is beſt to take counſel of Men, in the night of their age, when they have paſt through their troubles, difficulties and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold experiences, when as they are quiet, and ſedate, and there is not the noiſe and hurrying of paſſions to diſturb and diſtract them. And then old age is a fit age for the doing of good in regard of the prayers of old Men, I ſhould ordinarily chuſe, a young mans ſtrength and an old mans prayers to be employed for me. I count it a choice bleſſing to have a ſtock of prayers going in an old mans heart, for me; God loves to hear the prayers of his old ſervants, when the hands of old <hi>Moſes</hi> were up, his prayers were acceptable, though his hands were <hi>held up;</hi> we make much of the words of a dying man, and God eminently regards them. Hence old men are wont to give their bleſſings. <hi>i e.</hi> to pray for bleſſings from God: old <hi>Jacob</hi> bleſſed <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Old age is highly commendable for its ſafety. And old Saint hath paſſed through thoſe dangerous ſtorms and difficulties that a poor young one is now ſail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing toward; he hath done living almoſt, the other is now going and beginning to live; a young Man is happy, that doth live well, but an old an is happier, that <hi>hath lived</hi> well, he is by death beyond the temptations, the difficulties, the paſſions, that a young man lies ingaged to, and this is the <hi>fourth Corollary,</hi> that old age is a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 6.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>6</label> Though the coming to the grave in a <hi>full age,</hi> in a age wherein one is like to a <hi>ſhock</hi> of ripe Corn, be a <hi>promiſe,</hi> yet is it to be underſtood rightly; all Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple do not alwayes die in <hi>full age,</hi> in regard either of civill or natural fulneſſe; but yet if even <hi>ſuch a</hi> fulneſſe be good for them, they ſhall have it; and it ſhall note be
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115033:20"/>beſtowed, if it be not for their good. <hi>Honour thy father and thy mother, (as the Lord thy God hath commanded thee) that thy dayes may be prolonged, and that it may go well with thee.</hi> Mark that Deut. 5.16. <hi>If it ſhall go well with thee.</hi> Gods people ſhall have old age, if God ſee it may make for their welfare, God ſometime ſees that old age would tend to the outward trouble and miſery of his ſervants, by war, captivity poverty, famine, ſo that it would not be a <hi>good old age;</hi> and therefore he in mercy denies it them. <hi>Joſiah</hi> was taken away,<note place="margin">2 King. 22.20.</note> before he was an old man, that he might <hi>not ſee the evil that ſhould come upon the place</hi> where he lived, or much more if God ſees by old age, that they ſhall be brought under temptations which (it may be) they are not able to overcome, he will not ſuffer them to go out to battle in their old age, as the people ſaid concerning <hi>David, as the Lord lives thou ſhalt not go out to battle, leſt the light of Iſrael go out:</hi> if God ſees that thou ſhalt meet with ſuch great ſtormes and tempeſts as thou art not able to withſtand, he will take thee to himſelf, and ſhelter thee in the grave. In a word, if Gods people be taken away before they are old, and have <hi>a full age,</hi> they are taken away unto <hi>a full age,</hi> unto the full age of <hi>grace</hi> and glory in Heaven. God will give them an <hi>eternall life,</hi> and is not God in that way, as good as his word in promiſing a long life, and are they any loſers? doth God break his promiſe in not giving them an <hi>old age</hi> in this world, if he give them an <hi>everlaſting age</hi> in the next? If thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had promiſed thee an acre or two of Land lying in a barren Heath, or Common, and afterwards (in ſtead thereof) gives thee a thouſand acres of rich Meadow, doth he break his promiſes with thee, if the Lord promiſe to give an old age, and in ſtead thereof give thee Heaven
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115033:21"/>and Eternall life, doth he not exceed his own promiſe as well as thy merit? That man breaks not his word, who having promiſed ten pieces of braſſe, gives inſtead of theſe an hundred pieces of gold: as <hi>Herod,</hi> when he promiſed <hi>half his Kingdom</hi> unto the daughter of <hi>Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dias,</hi> if he had given the whole Kingdom to her, he had not broke his promiſe, ſo when God promiſes not <hi>half</hi> nor the thouſand part of Heaven in promiſing long life, he falls not ſhort, but goes beyond his word, in beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Eternity of bliſſe. Beſides, God promiſes no good to his people in this world but that which ſhall be a furtherance to the obtaining of the chiefeſt good; if it be a <hi>bond</hi> to binde them to God, not if it be a <hi>ſnare to</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trap and hinder them from God, and he ſhould be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt and unkind in beſtowing an earthly good upon thee, if he ſees that it would ſtop thee from that which is Eternall. <hi>Ita diſponit de minimo ut non fiat periculum de maximo.</hi> God ſo diſpoſeth of thee here in regard of this, that thou mayeſt not be in danger of loſing Eternall life.</p>
            <p>In a word remember, the people of God die in a <hi>full age,</hi> whenſoever they die! though they die young, yet they are imbalmed for <hi>Eternity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Beſides they are ſatisfied and filled with their daies: the wicked never live out <hi>half their dayes,</hi> no when they live to be never ſo old; the godly live <hi>fully,</hi> though they die never ſo young: they die old, if not according to the courſe of nature, yet according to the courſe of their deſires.</p>
            <p>Laſtly,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>7</label> 
               <hi>Old age is not to be abuſed by the aged themſelves,</hi> 1. It muſt not be abuſed by <hi>ignorance,</hi> how ſhamefull is it to ſee a man whoſe hairs and wrinckles ſpeak him an hundred, but his knowledge of Chriſt ſpeaks him not
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115033:21"/>ten, who is an <hi>alphabetical</hi> old man (as one calls him,) who is in the worſe ſence <hi>twice a child,</hi> that doth not know his right hand from his left in Religion, that though he ſhould be a teacher <hi>of others, had need him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be taught the firſt principles of the Oracles of God.</hi> 2. Abuſe not old age by <hi>prophaneneſſe,</hi> oh how ſad is it for a <hi>black</hi> heart to lodge under a <hi>hoary</hi> head, for one to be <hi>ripe</hi> for the grave, and ripe for hell at the ſame time. Let old men take heed of recollecting former youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full follies with delight. O let them be more bitter to <hi>remember</hi> then ever they have been <hi>ſweet</hi> to commit, 3. Abuſe it not by <hi>unprofitableneſſe,</hi> and negligence, what art thou almoſt at thy Haven, and doeſt thou ſail ſo ſlowly? art thou in danger of loſing Eternity, and doeſt thou run no faſter. For ſhame, old Chriſtians up and be doing you have but a little paper to write in, oh write the cloſer: improve your time; you have but a little time to work, your candle is almoſt burnt out. O work the faſter; your ſun is almoſt ſet, O labour with the more Chriſtian diligence and vigor.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>THus I have given you the Application of this part of the Text to our ſelves,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> give me leave to ſpeak in the next place ſomething in the Application thereof to the occaſion. And indeed to it I might here apply both the Parts of the Text. Out of the former part you have heard that the grave is the <hi>Port and place</hi> even of Saints: here is a Saint, an old eminent Saint, and yet (you ſee) the grave is his place to which he is arrived he is laid down in this his bed, and <hi>ſleeps in the Lord,</hi> his grace could not exempt him from the grave: And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God hath given him a <hi>grave,</hi> an honourable peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115033:22"/>buriall: he is not buried as ſome have been in the bellies of beaſts, but laid to reſt in the boſome of the earth: he is not a <hi>portion for foxes, but</hi> a ſpectacle of Saints, I ſay of Saints, who love his memory, to whom as his Doctrine was profitable, ſo now is his memory ſweet and Savoury, he hath perfumed the world with the ſweet ointment of his preaching and example, and now he is taken out of it, the Savour is left behind; the great numbers of ſpectators and tears that attend his Funerall, ſpeak the honourableneſſe of his interment. But then he <hi>comes</hi> to his grave too, and ſo likewiſe he is the man in my Text<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this ſervant of Chriſt, <hi>came willingly,</hi> he was not pulled and dragged to the grave: death was his familiar acquaintance, it was his privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge as well as his <hi>task;</hi> when his good Siſter ſaid to him in his ſickneſſe <hi>Brother I am afraid to leave you alone; why Siſter</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I ſhall I am ſure be with Jeſus Chriſt when I die:</hi> the meditation of death was not more frequent then ſweet to him: he chewed upon this morſel, death, every day: he did not go about to ſwallow it down all at once (as ſome fooliſh ſinners do) when he came to die, for then he would have found this great morſel too big for him; but by holy Meditation he took it down dayly piece by piece; he lookt (as it were) ſo frequently from the top of the maſt into the ſea of death, that at length it ſeemed to him not onely a not aſtoniſhing, but an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, familiar, pleaſing ſpectacle. His ſoul was upon the wing, and was bent heavenward, even when it was in the cage of his poor carkaſſe, and when the violence of his diſeaſe began to break open that cage, I ſay not how patient, but how joyfull was he! much he longed <hi>to be with Chriſt,</hi> and in effect he would ſay, <hi>why is his Chariot ſo long a coming;</hi> well, he is <hi>in the grave,</hi> and he is <hi>come</hi> to the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115033:22"/>grave. Thus the <hi>former</hi> part of my text is applicable to him. But that which I principally intended, was the application of the <hi>ſecond</hi> Part of the Text to him: namely, the <hi>ſeaſonableneſſe</hi> of the godly mans coming to the grave<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Come he is to the grave like the man in my Text, in a <hi>full age</hi> like as a <hi>ſhock of corn,</hi> &amp;c. If you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider his birth, this ripe <hi>ſhock of corn,</hi> Doctor <hi>William Gouge</hi> brought this day to the barn of the grave, ſprang at firſt from Mr. <hi>Thomas Gouge</hi> of <hi>Stratford Bow,</hi> a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of eminent <hi>quality,</hi> and of Singular piety in his generation. If you look upon him in the <hi>growing</hi> years of his youth, he was an <hi>Eaton</hi> Scholer, and he was there fitted for the Univerſity, and ſent to <hi>Kings Colledge in Cambridge,</hi> where he was ſo <hi>Studious,</hi> and <hi>profited</hi> ſo much by his ſtudies, that he was made <hi>modorator</hi> in the <hi>Sophiſters</hi> Schooles. He took all his degrees in their order, and did perform all thoſe acts, that were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of him publikely, for the taking thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees He was a cloſe Student in the Univerſity, and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent for his knowledge in the learned <hi>Languages,</hi> and in the Arts, very well verſed in Logick and <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> of both which he was choſen the Lecturer in his Colledge. Nor yet was he there leſſe noted for his <hi>piety,</hi> even in his younger years, he was not once abſent (neither morning nor Evening) from the publike and ſolemn worſhip of God in the Colledge performed twice every day, for the ſpace of nine whole years together. He read <hi>fifteen Chapters</hi> in the Bible every day, and when he lay awake in the night, his courſe was to Meditate of what he had read in the day-time, ſo deceiving the tediouſneſs of his <hi>waking</hi> and depriving himſelf alſo ſometimes of the <hi>ſweetneſſe</hi> of his ſleeping hours, though by a better and greater ſweetneſſe. Thus you have ſeen him in his
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115033:23"/>
                  <hi>growing</hi> years. Next look upon him in the <hi>full eare</hi> when he had taken all this pains to furniſh himſelf with the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Jewels of Univerſity-learning and accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, he was fit to come into the <hi>Canaan</hi> of the Church to deck &amp; adorn the ſpouſe of Chriſt: he entred into the Miniſtry, when he was in the thirty ſecond <hi>yeer of</hi> his age: an age ſutable to that calling which being ſo weighty, he durſt not undertake raſhly, and unadviſedly, (I wiſh all thoſe whom it concerns would take notice of it, and example by him herein:) he <hi>laid up,</hi> before the <hi>laid out,</hi> he firſt laboured to fit himſelf with endowments, and not till then, did he put himſelf upon imployment. He was <hi>a ſcribe instructed unto the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 13.52.</note> 
                  <hi>like an ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſholder which bringeth forth out of his treaſure things new and old.</hi> He ſucceeded that eminently faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of Jeſus Chriſt, Mr. <hi>Stephen Egerton</hi> in the charge of <hi>Black-Fryars,</hi> to which he was unanimouſly choſen. But (as I ſaid) I principally look upon him in his ripe and <hi>full age</hi> And firſt God beſtowed upon him a <hi>Civil maturity</hi> and ripeneſſe of age:<note place="margin">His Civil maturity or fulneſſe of age.</note> Firſt, he had much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, How great was the confluence of hearers which in former times not onely from all parts of this famous City, but of many parts of <hi>England,</hi> frequented his Lectures at <hi>Black-fryars</hi> (for ſo great was the flame of his pains, that he heated thoſe who ſat a great way off from it) and when the godly Chriſtians of thoſe times came to <hi>London,</hi> they thought not their buſineſſe <hi>done</hi> unleſs they had been at <hi>Black-fryars</hi> Lectures: and great was the benefit which many godly people, and young Miniſters profeſſed that they (then) reapt from his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. How was this place wherein you honour him at his death by your unwonted and great numbers, thronged in his life time! and ſo great were the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115033:23"/>that here met to hear him, and withall his tender compaſſion toward the multitudes of his hearers, that out of this Pulpit he was wont (before he began his Sermons) to obſerve what Pues were empty, and to command his Clark to open them, for the eaſe of thoſe who thronged in the Iſles. He was worthily not only for his years, but his prudence, and abilities accounted, a <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> among the <hi>London</hi> Miniſters, and honoured as ſuch: he was choſen to be a member of the Reverend Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of Divines, &amp; was one of thoſe learned Divines who wrote lately the large Annotations upon the Bible. He was for his wiſdom and faithfulneſſe, worthily choſen a Truſtee for buying in impropriations, wherein he approved himſelf moſt faithfull and conſcientiouſly carefull to diſcharge the truſt committed to him: nor was he altogether without the bleſſing of a <hi>fulneſſe</hi> in reſpect of a wealthy and plentifull Eſtate in the world. I know there are ſome who look upon a Miniſters <hi>wealth</hi> as his <hi>crime</hi> (when they can eſpie no other) who out of <hi>covetouſneſſe,</hi> care not how little they themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow upon Miniſters, and out of <hi>envie</hi> are readie to voice them to poſſeſſe much more then they do, and therefore do not inſtead of an hundred ſet down fiftie, but inſtead of fifty, ſet down a thouſand: many ſuch <hi>back friends,</hi> hath this reverend man met with; for his Eſtate, though it were not ſo ſmall as either for him or his, to be <hi>aſhamed</hi> of, yet neither was it ſo <hi>great</hi> as for any to <hi>envy,</hi> or as ſome have reported. For thus much I can aſſure you from thoſe who very well know, that his <hi>perſonall</hi> Eſtate is found ſhort, by ſome hundreds of pounds, of his Legacies and gifts, &amp; his <hi>reall</hi> Eſtate is not half ſo much as ſundry have voiced it. And yet had he
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115033:24"/>been ſuch an one as ſome have maliciouſly and falſly cenſured him, an uſurer, he might have had, though leſſe grace, yet more money, and yet as much grace alſo, as (I fear) moſt of thoſe have, who ſo unworthily have aſperſt him. This I can aſſure you from many who fully knew his courſe, and Eſtate (particularly from the mouth of his eldeſt ſon, my reverend brother) who can teſtifie what I am about to ſay in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular upon oath, that in all his life-time, he never did either directly or indirectly, neither by himſelf or any other for him, put any money to uſe, and ſo far was he from doing ſo, that ſundry can teſtifie, he was ſcarce ever out of debt; for he had divers chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren before the inheritance which he had by his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther came to him, and from the time of his fathers death, till his children came of age, he laid out, for his brother, ſiſters, and their children, above two thouſand pounds; yea in thoſe times, wherein he was charged to have put money to uſe, he paid intereſt for ſix hundred pounds, which with the principall, he himſelf paid, though it were anothers debt: and for theſe 20. years laſt paſt, he purchaſed not one foot of Land, unleſſe ten pounds <hi>per annum;</hi> and he would often ſay that after his death, the world would know how much they were miſtaken in judging of his Eſtate. And yet through the bleffing of God upon him, he was both rich in <hi>contentment</hi> with his Eſtate while he lived, and left a comfortable ſubſiſtence behind him for all his ſurviving children when he died, and as his children (I truſt) ſhall finde the bleſſing of the <hi>latter,</hi> ſo did he in his life-time, expreſſe the grace of the <hi>former,</hi> in refuſing great and to him, inregard of his naturall diſpoſition (as
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115033:24"/>he oft profeſſed to me) deſirable preferment (as particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly that of the Provoſtſhip of <hi>Kings Colledge in Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> offered him by an honourable hand) much more advantagious in worldly reſpects, then that of his Living of <hi>Black Fryers,</hi> and this he did for the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der reſpect which he bare to the ſouls of his people, to which God had called him.</p>
               <p>But for no fulneſſe was his age ſo eminent,<note place="margin">His ſpiritual fulneſſe of age.</note> as for that which principally deſerves commendation. I mean <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual fulneſſe.</hi> This I ſhall briefly conſider, both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect 1. Of what <hi>grace he had,</hi> and 2. <hi>What good he did.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. For the former. In the <hi>general,</hi> he had received of the <hi>fulneſſe of Chriſt,</hi> that <hi>grace for grace</hi> whereby he was made meet for glory,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and which was ſuitable to his ſtate and ſtation, both as a Chriſtian and a Miniſter: but more <hi>particularly,</hi> there were <hi>three</hi> beautiful gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which eminently ſhin'd in this godly man; in which he ſeem'd <hi>higher by the head and ſhoulders,</hi> then other Chriſtians, and then moſt Miniſters. 1. The firſt was the grace of <hi>humility;</hi> though others knew not when his face did <hi>not ſhine,</hi> yet he knew not when it <hi>did.</hi> And yet he eaſily could obſerve the leaſt glymps or appearance of any worth in another, and would acknowledge it. He knew not that worth which had a beam-like big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in himſelf, but he eaſily eſpied and reſpected that of good which was but as a <hi>mote</hi> in another. This I have alwayes (almoſt) obſerved in him ſince it was my hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py unhappineſſe to have occaſion to be ſo frequently in his company by reaſon of my employment among his people. He was, as its ſaid of <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, high in employments and abilities, low in his diſpoſition and reſentment of his worth. So
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115033:25"/>eminent was his humility, that he charged his Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to whom he committed the care of his Funeral, that there ſhould bee no <hi>Green-ſtaff</hi> laid upon his Herſe, though this was the uſual reſpect given to thoſe who in their life-time had been Governours of <hi>Bridewell</hi> (one of which number, yea, and Benefactor to the houſe this worthy Doctor was) and that he ſhould not affix any Eſcucheons to his Herſe, though he were a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man anciently deſcended; as if he had thought that the <hi>poverty of Chriſt was his patrimony</hi> (as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaid) and Coat of Arms,<note place="margin">Paupertas Chriſti meum patrimonium. <hi>Ambr.</hi>
                  </note> and his intereſt in him, his greateſt and beſt atchievement, or as if both living and dead, he would be (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks) <hi>clothed with humility.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. A <hi>ſecond grace</hi> which eminently appeared in him was that grace of <hi>Faith.</hi> I obſerved in him as great a ſtudy to advance <hi>Chriſt</hi> as to debaſe <hi>himſelf;</hi> frequently (of late) I have heard him ſay, <hi>When I look upon my ſelf, I ſee nothing but emptineſs &amp; weakneſs, But when I look upon Chriſt, I ſee nothing but fulneſſe and ſufficiency:</hi> when the hand of his <hi>body</hi> was weak and ſhaking, that of his <hi>ſoul (faith)</hi> was ſtrong and ſteddy. When he could not hold the cup at the Sacrament, nor evenly carry it to his mouth, by reaſon of his weakneſſe and ſhaking, with what a firm and fixed affiance did he lay hold upon Chriſt, and with what a ſtrong and eager appetite, did he apply the blood of Chriſt to his ſoul! And how ſweetly have I heard him breathe out joyful thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings for his refreſhment by the blood of Chriſt, when he was returned to his houſe, after the Lords Supper; when he could hardly creep with his body to the place where it was celebrated, nay, was forced to make uſe of the ſtrength and ſupport of others to hold him up,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115033:25"/>his faith ſwiftly ran, nay, was upon the <hi>wing</hi> in carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to Chriſt. When worldly ſupports failed him, his health, ſtrength forſook him, he made JESUS CHRIST the <hi>ſtaff</hi> of his old age, oft profeſſing as his great miſery and impotency without him, ſo his holy and humble recumbency upon him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A third grace wherewith this holy man was (even to common obſervation) beautified, was that of <hi>pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> under the hand of God: the truth is, he was of a <hi>meek and quiet ſpirit</hi> toward man. I have not heard that ever he was moved to anger by any injuries or diſgraceful and falſe reports wherewith hee was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſt. They were as bullets ſhot againſt a mud-wall, which there ſink and dye: when dirt was moſt abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively caſt into his face, there never (in my obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) was blood fetcht into his face, by wrath and paſſion: he was truly meek in ſpirit. So amiable was the meekneſſe of his carriage toward his wife, that for twenty two yeers (for ſo long they lived to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether) there was never heard any one word pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from him toward her, ſounding like an angry one. But for his patience under the afflicting hand of <hi>God,</hi> I know not whether it were more admirable or imitable. Though by reaſon of the bitterneſſe of his pains by the ſtone and ſharpneſſe of urine, and that <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thalis arundo</hi> (as he oft called it) that deadly arrow in his ſide (which hee knew could never be pluckt out of it but by death) I mean his <hi>Aſthma</hi> or difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of breathing, which he got by an exceſſive cold in attending upon publick employment: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, I ſay, by reaſon of theſe, I have heard him groan a thouſand times, yet never did I hear
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115033:26"/>him grumble once. Never did he complain of God for his ſuffering, though oft of himſelf for ſinning. Never did I hear him ſay <hi>great ſufferer!</hi> but often <hi>great ſinner!</hi> and yet he would overtake that expreſſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, with the diſcourſing of, and comforting himſelf in a <hi>great Saviour:</hi> and in the depth of his torments he would ſay, well, yet <hi>in all theſe, there is nothing of Hell or Gods wrath.</hi> His ſufferings never were ſo deep but he could ſee to the bottom of them. And as the grace he <hi>had</hi> was great,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ſo <hi>ſecondly,</hi> in this <hi>ſpiritual fulneſſe</hi> of his age, I conſider the <hi>good he did:</hi> Look upon him in his family, and there you will finde him both indulgent toward the bodies of his children, and ſervants, and yet eſpecially careful of their ſouls, witneſſe his conſtant labour in catechizing them, and daily dropping upon them with holy inſtructions. He was the <hi>husband of one wife,</hi> a widower eight and twenty yeers, and he had thirteen children by that his one and onely wife, whereof eight lived to mans and womans eſtate: all his ſons he brought up to learning, deſiring that they might have all been im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in the Miniſtery, it being that calling which to him was as full of pleaſure as imployment; his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours wherein, he went through ſo delightfully, that he oft profeſſed to mee, that the greateſt pleaſure which he took in the world, was in the employments of his calling, in regard whereof, he hath told great perſons, and particularly the <hi>Lord Keeper,</hi> that he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied not the greatneſſe of his place; and yet he was a very cloſe (I had almoſt ſaid a ſevere) ſtudent, and was at his ſtudy, every morning (Winter and Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer during his health) by five a clock in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115033:26"/>and alwayes by four in the ſummer, and oft ſooner, ſo that he had done that which might have been counted a dayes work, before many began their ſtudy. And indeed <hi>it was his deſire to perform his ſecret worſhipping of God before day-light,</hi> that ſo he might have the benefit of the whole day for his ſtudy, and he would oft ſay (as <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> ſpake concerning the ſmith) that he was aſhamed that thoſe of others callings, ſhould be at their work, before he was at <hi>his:</hi> ſo that none could give him that reproof which I have read a certain Religious man gave to a Biſhop who ſlept too long a mornings,<note place="margin">Surrexerunt paſſeres et ſter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unt pontifices?</note> 
                  <hi>the ſparrows are up, and chirping and yet the Biſhop is in bed and ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> (If he laboured to make the ſleepy Biſhop aſhamed by the riſing of the <hi>ſparro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> oh how ſhould ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Miniſters be aſhamed of their idleneſſe, when they hear of this painfull ſervant of Chriſt Doctor <hi>Gouge</hi>) The Pariſh of <hi>Black-fryars</hi> will be a ſtanding and a conſtant witneſſe of his delighting to do good. At his firſt coming to it, the old Church in regard of the great thronging from all parts to his Sermons, being found far too ſmall for the auditory, he procured fifteen hundred pounds by collections at his Lectures and by Letters written to his Friends, whereby it was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged to this Stately and Beautifull ſtructure without any briefes at all. He was ever very Charitable to the (eſpecially) godly poor, of which (yet) he would make no report vain gloriouſly. In his life time, he ſet a part as a<note n="*" place="margin">His own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion.</note> 
                  <hi>ſacred ſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k,</hi> a portion for the poor, proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to all his receipts, which he faithfully diſtributed. He preached for many years together <hi>thrice</hi> (conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) every week, and how pithy clear, Judicious his
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115033:27"/>Sermons were, not onely the confluence, and applauſe of his Auditors, but eſpecially the benefit which they reaped from them will abundantly teſtifie. For five and forty years together, he did once every moneth ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, not ſo much as once interrupting that courſe; and if upon ſome urgent occaſion, he was neceſſitated to be from his charge, he would not fail to be preſent at it upon the Sacrament-day though his other employments never ſo loudly called him off. In a great part of the fore-mentioned long ſpace of yeers (during the time of Prelatical Innovations) he was a ſweet refreſhing ſhade and ſhelter, and even as ſtreams in a dry ſcorching wilderneſſe, to the old godly Puritanes (now accounted to be a name of honour, though heretofore a nickname of diſgrace) by admitting them to the Lords Supper at his Congregation, who could not either at all, or at leaſt purely (in regard of Superſtitious geſtures genuflexions, &amp;c.) enjoy that ordinance at home. He preached to his people by his life as well as by his lip: he was (as one ſpeaks of <hi>John Baptiſt</hi>) <hi>all voice,</hi> and ſuch in his practice as well as his Pulpit. How unblameable, temperate, holy, was his deportment in all places! how exemplary was he to the flock! He was not like ſome of whom I have heard, that <hi>they preach ſo well, that its pity they ſhould ever be out of the Pulpit, but they live ſo ill, that its pity they ſhould ever be in the Pulpit.</hi> He was as of a moſt ſweet even and peaceable temper himſelf, ſo of much for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvardneſſe to compoſe, and (vvhich is not every peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able mans happineſſe) much prudence in compoſing all differences among his people, among vvhom he
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:115033:27"/>was (as ſome of them have told me) as it were <hi>a Juſtice of Peace,</hi> as well as a <hi>Miniſter of Peace.</hi> If he could not (as what man can) hinder diſſentions from being born, he would not ſuffer them to be long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lived.</p>
               <p>As it was his contentment and crown laboriouſly, during his healthfull years, to Preach, ſo notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his forementioned pains and infirmities, he did Preach, as long as he was able to get up into the Pulpit, and this (I queſtion whither it can be a paraleld) Commendation, I ſhall adde, <hi>He Preached ſo long as that it was a greater difficulty for him to go up into the Pulpit, then either to make or Preach a Sermon,</hi> and that both becauſe of the growing weakneſſe of his body, and the conſtant if not increaſing ability of his parts and judgement, even to his laſt. In ſnort, he would have accounted it a mercy, if he who Preacht ſo much in his life, might alſo have dyed Preaching. To all this I might adjoyn his great induſtry in, and uſefulneſſe by publiſhing in Print many excellent and pithy diſcourſes. Here I might mention his Printed Catechiſme, his clear and judicious Annotations upon that part of the Bible contained from the firſt of <hi>Samuel</hi> to <hi>Job.</hi> His book called <hi>the whole Armour of God,</hi> another called <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtical duties,</hi> his Comment on the 116. Pſa<note n="*" place="margin">A Treatiſe.</note> Gods <hi>three arrows,</hi> and his Exquiſite (and I queſtion whether to be paraleld) <hi>expoſition of the Lords Prayer,</hi> and that Elabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Comment of his upon the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> which (after many yeers preaching) he went through in his Sermons at <hi>Black-Fryars,</hi> and which he fully pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the Preſſe, before his death, excepting one half Chapter; a work of excellent worth, both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115033:28"/>the <hi>Subject</hi> (noble, and difficult) and the great paines and dexterity of the <hi>Commentator;</hi> and which being now in the Preſſe ſhall (I truſt) ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee the light, though in regard of its bigneſſe the coming forth thereof cannot be ſo ſpeedy, as is deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and as the book will (I am confident) when publiſht, be uſeful. To conclude this head of his <hi>ſpiritual fulneſſe</hi> of age, he was one who may be fitly called both <hi>one of a thouſand,</hi> and alſo <hi>a thouſand men in one,</hi> for his excellent endowments, for his uſefulneſſe in his employments.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly and laſtly,<note place="margin">His natural fulneſſe.</note> for his <hi>natural fulneſſe</hi> and ripeneſſe of age; he was one to whom my Text is applicable in that particular alſo. He was aged ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty nine when he died, ſo that he had the full age, which (as I ſaid before) was <hi>ſenectus ſera</hi> a late,<note place="margin">Senectus ſera.</note> long age. But then I confeſſe, he runs not fully parallel with my Text in reſpect of that branch of <hi>naturall ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> of age, which (I told you) was <hi>Senectus ſana,</hi> a <hi>ſtrong, hayl, vigorous,</hi> diſeaſeleſſe old age. No; his forementioned diſeaſes, and bodily infirmities of the <hi>Stone</hi> and <hi>Aſthma,</hi> here would make me halt, were it not for this double conſideration (in regard of which I cannot onely excuſe his crazineſſe in old age, but even highly commend him under it.) 1. His diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes came not upon him, <hi>in,</hi> much leſſe <hi>by</hi> any ſinful or unwarrantable courſes; envie it ſelf dares not tax him of intemperance, in eating, drinking, paſtimes, (hee hath been oft heard to ſay hee never took a journey meerly for pleaſure in all his life;) No, his diſeaſes came either by his laboriouſneſſe in ſtudy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, preaching, watching, or attending in all wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:115033:28"/>and ſeaſons, upon his work at the Aſſembly. He received his wounds in his Maſters ſervice, they were all ſcars of honour, he was not worn with ruſt, but whetting. 2. This I ſhall adde as his honour under his crazineſſe of body, that when he was moſt decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit and feeble, he had the bleſſing of a <hi>Senectus ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Senectus ſana.</note> an <hi>hayl ſtrong old age,</hi> in regard of his parts of minde, his intellectuals, which were as vivid, quick, and vigorous in reaſoning and diſputing as when he was fourty yeers of age, in the greateſt of his bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtrength. And this few can more fully know then my ſelf, by reaſon of my frequent occaſions of converſing with him, eſpecially upon the Lords dayes, when often after the evening Sermon propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thoſe Theological doubts to him, concerning which I deſired to draw forth his apprehenſions; yea, of this which I now ſay, the whole Miniſtry of <hi>London</hi> will atteſt the truth from their own experience, by cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to their mindes that learned, cleer, and polite Sermon of his, lately preached in Latin at <hi>Sion Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> before them all. And the truth is, this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of the uſe of his reaſon, and abilities of minde, was the reaſon why he adventured ſo long as he did, to frequent the publick Aſſembly, yea, and to preach, notwithſtanding the crazineſſe and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of his body. I can ſtudy my Sermon, ſaid he, I can preach my Sermon, and ſhall I forbear preaching becauſe I am ſo weak as not to be able to go? I will be carryed rather, and carryed he oft was. So that indeed the blade of his minde was too ſharp for the ſheath of his body, the wine too ſtrong for the cask, and his abilities of minde too vigorous
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:115033:29"/>for his weak diſeaſed carkaſs. I now draw to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion: ſome will ſay, I have not commended him <hi>enough,</hi> I confeſſe it, nor can I. Others that I have in his commendation ſaid <hi>too much,</hi> I confeſſe it too, but my meaning is, <hi>too much</hi> perhaps for their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, <hi>too much</hi> (I ſear) for their imitation. But ſince he who thought that ſeventy nine yeers on earth were not, nay that eternity in heaven, is not too much to ſerve and praiſe his and our Lord, let not us think that half an hour is too much to ſcatter a few flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers on his Herſe, they being ſuch as were planted by his own labour, or ſuch rather which grew out of his own worth.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>FOr the marg. note pag. 8. <hi>r.</hi> the ſecond point of the firſt branch, <hi>p.</hi> 14. marg. r. <hi>accedant non adhaereant, p.</hi> 15. <hi>l.</hi> 17. <hi>r.</hi> comprehended, <hi>l.</hi> 22. <hi>r.</hi> meetneſſe, <hi>p.</hi> 17. marg. <hi>r. vulgatam, p.</hi> 38. <hi>l.</hi> 26 <hi>r.</hi> fifth.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Theſe books are lately printed, and are ſold at the Ball in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard.</head>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Jenkyns</hi> ſecond part of his Expoſition of the whole Epiſtle of <hi>Jude.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Kendal</hi> of the Perſeverance of the Saints, in anſwer to Mr. <hi>John Goodwin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Sheffeild</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> under that clear and glorious reſemblance of the Sun, <hi>Mal,</hi> 4 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jus Divinum Miniſterii,</hi> by the Provincial Aſſembly of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon preached at the Funeral of Dr. <hi>Hill,</hi> Maſter of <hi>Trinity</hi> Colledge in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> by Dr. <hi>Tuckney.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:115033:29"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
